New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Glass Negative Collection 2007.0055
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Glass Negative Collection
circa 1900-1922.
2007.0055
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
4.0 Linear feet
This collection consists of 149 plate glass negatives of images of railroad cars, primarily those of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, from the early 20th century. Many of the negatives are exterior shots of coaches, dining cars, state room/sleeping cars, parlor cars, and freight cars. The collection also includes interior views of these various railroad cars. One image of particular interest is an overhead view of a gondola car with a locomotive in the background.
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company.
History
For almost one hundred years the New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, was the primary means of passenger and freight transportation in southern New England. Chartered in 1872, this merger between the New York & New Haven and Hartford & New Haven railroads later included the long desired rail link between Boston and New York. Approximately one hundred small independent railroads were built in southern New England between 1826 and the 1880s. By 1904, the majority were absorbed into the vast New Haven system. At its peak in 1929, the New Haven Railroad owned and operated 2,131 miles of track throughout eastern New York, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island.
The local railroad lines that eventually became part of the New Haven system developed in response to local business and transportation needs. Unlike the Western states, where railroads preceded and shaped settlement, in the Northeast they served primarily to link existing towns, businesses, and markets. The New Haven system thus developed as a result of numerous consolidations and mergers. The New Haven traced its founding to 1826, when one of its predecessor companies originated, but the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad was not chartered until 1872. The company followed the pattern of consolidation established by the Pennsylvania Railroad and other companies, particularly after 1889, when major lines in Connecticut, Rhode Island, and southern Massachusetts provided a strong network linking New York and Boston. By 1890, company revenue exceeded $100,000,000 per year, and the New Haven employed 4,000 people to serve twelve million passengers annually.
This success led a wealthy group of New York investors, headed by J. P. Morgan, to seek and gain control of the New Haven's board. In 1903, Morgan installed Charles Mellen as president of the railroad. Together Morgan and Mellen set out to achieve a complete monopoly of transportation in New England. Substantial improvements to the system were made during the Mellen years, including electrification of rail lines between Woodlawn, New York, and New Haven, Connecticut, and construction of a power generating plant in Cos Cob, Connecticut. These accomplishments, however, were overshadowed by Morgan's ambitious schemes to dominate all modes of transportation in New England. Steamboat lines, trolley companies, and other railroad lines were purchased regardless of price and incorporated into the New Haven system.
An investigation of the New Haven's activities by Louis Brandeis in 1907 revealed the overextended railroad was on the verge of financial collapse. Morgan's death in 1913 and Mellen's subsequent resignation brought to a close a stormy period in the New Haven's history.
During the First World War, all of the railroads in the United States, including the New Haven Railroad, were operated by the federal government. After the war, under Edward Pearson, President through 1928, the railroad was able to recover partially, despite increasing competition from automobiles, by sharing in the national economic growth of the 1920s. The company tried to meet this transportation competition by forming the New England Transportation Company, which operated a fleet of trucks and buses. Recovery of the New Haven, however, was cut short by the Depression of the 1930s, and in 1935 the New Haven plunged into bankruptcy. The company remained in trusteeship until 1947, when it returned to private ownership.
A series of struggles for control of the company in the post World War II period severely weakened the management of the company and its ability to adapt to changes in the transportation industry. The completion of the Connecticut Turnpike and other superhighways and the start of air shuttle service between Boston and New York intensified competition. The company's historic liability as a railroad overburdened with many short, costly branch lines further accelerated its decline.
On 7 July 1961, the New Haven Railroad once again went into receivership. A seven year trusteeship period followed, culminating in the absorption of the New Haven in the Penn Central system on 1 January 1969. Three years later the Penn Central itself collapsed into bankruptcy. The former components of the New Haven Railroad were divided among several entities. Freight service was assumed by Conrail when it was formed in 1976, although the Providence & Worcester also provided freight service on portions of the former New Haven, as did a few other operators. Passenger commuter service was funded by the New York Metropolitan Transit Authority and the Connecticut Department of Transportation. Long-haul passenger service was provided by Amtrak beginning in 1971. After 1976 passenger commuter service was operated by Conrail. In 1982, the United States Congress passed legislation that forced Conrail to divest itself of its commuter rail lines. On 1 January 1983, Metro-North Commuter Railroad, under joint ownership of the states of New York and Connecticut, took over all commuter passenger service. Amtrak continued to handle all long-haul passenger service.
The history of the New Haven Railroad reveals a company formed by one of the classic merger and consolidation patterns of the late 19th century, which was later unable to respond effectively to major changes in the transportation industry. The company's rapid growth, collapse, temporary recovery, and final dissolution offer a dramatic story, with government regulation, internal management decisions, and market competition playing important roles in the company's history.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 149 plate glass negatives of images of railroad cars, primarily those of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, from the early 20th century. Many of the negatives are exterior shots of coaches, dining cars, state room/sleeping cars, parlor cars, and freight cars. The collection also includes interior views of these various railroad cars. One image of particular interest is an overhead view of a gondola car with a locomotive in the background.
The negatives were described with the generous contribution of Mr. J. W. Swanberg.
Arrangement
Series I: Glass Negatives, includes views of the following types of cars in the following order; steam car, coaches, combination cars, baggage cars, parlor cars, sleeping/stateroom cars, dining cars, business cars, invalid cars, freight cars and wrecking cars.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
Prints have been made for each glass negative in the collection and are available as a reference set. The original glass negatives are not available for use due to their fragility.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased from a dealer in May 2007.
Negatives.; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Railroad Cars.
- Series I: Glass Negatives, circa 1900-1922
  - Steam car
    - 3/4 view of wooden steam car 1098 power truck end, has pilot (right side view), circa 1903 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 3/4 view of wooden steam car 1098 power truck end, has pilot (left side), circa 1903 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Coaches
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 7 with miller coupler, duckbill clerestory roof and wooden slated window covers, circa 1900 (Box 5:, Folder 3)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 55 with monitor roof, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Interior view of coach 55 with monitor roof, gas ceiling lamps and elegant baggage racks, circa 1900 (Box 5:, Folder 5)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 96 with miller coupler, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 105 with arched windows, built by Jackson and Sharp in 1892 (to caboose service on February 13, 1903), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 129 with semi arched windows, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 169, with split knuckle coupler, link attached (built by New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad in 1875, destroyed on April 24, 1916), circa 1900 (Box 5:, Folder 9)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 193 with miller coupler, ornamental windowtops, and sheet metal under roof ends (built by New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad in 1875, converted to work car 507322 on September 1, 1916), circa 1900 (Box 5:, Folder 10)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 251 with leaded colored glass windowtops (built in 1892; rebuilt on October 9, 1919), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 365 with raised metal lettering, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 365 with raised metal lettering, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 365 taken from diferent angle, with miller coupler, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 734, with round roof (built by Bradley in 1887 to work service 507030 on August 18, 1916), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Interior view of coach 734, with gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 784 with duckbill clerestory roof (possibly built by Berver and Diernell in 1881, renumbered 4862 and destroyed on March 24, 1916), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 784 with duckbill clerestory roof (possibly built by Berver and Diernell in 1881, renumbered 4862 and destroyed on March 24, 1916), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Interior view of suburban coach 784, with partly longitudinal seating, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 794 with closed vestibule, miller coupler, and ornamental windowtops (possibly built by Berver and Diernell in 1881, rebuilt on September 1, 1915, possibly in Bester, Washington, changed to regular car number 1985), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - Interior view of coach 794, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 853 with spoked wheels (built by Old Colony Railroad in 1881 in Islington, Massachusetts, September 15, 1915), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 954 with miller coupler (built by Wason in 1892 for Old Colony Railroad), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 980 with miller coupler and closed vestibule(built in 1896, rebuilt on March 5, 1910 by New Haven Light Construction), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 1088 with miller coupler (built in 1883 to workservice as car #518731 on September 28, 1918), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 1163 with miller coupler and closed vestibule, not opaqued, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 1163 with miller coupler and closed vestibule, opaqued, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Interior view of coach 1163 with gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - 3/4 view of suburban coach 1912 with spoked wheels, link and pin coupler, built to elevated car clearances, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
    - Interior view of suburban coach 1912 with some longitudinal seating subway ceiling straps, built to elevated car clearances by Wason Co. in 1891, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - 3/4 view of wooden coach 1920 with spoked wheels, built to elevated car clearances, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Interior view of coach 1920, built for elevated clearances, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
    - Interior view of coach showing coach seating with gas ceiling lamp, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Combination cars
    - 3/4 view of buffet/baggage car 2252 with decorative railings and miller coupler, photo taken from buffet end, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
    - Interior view of buffet/baggage car 2252 with stuffed chairs, writing desk, brass spitoons and stuffed double seats, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
    - 3/4 view of buffet/baggage car 2255 with decorative railings and miller coupler, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
    - Interior view of buffet/baggage car 2255 with stuffed individual and double chairs and gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
    - Interior view of buffet/baggage car 2255 with ornamental columns, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
    - 3/4 view of buffet/baggage car 2257 with narrow vestibule and miller coupler, not opaqued, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
    - 3/4 view of buffet/baggage car 2257 photo taken from buffet end, circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
    - 3/4 view of buffet/baggage car 2259 with decorative railings and miller coupler (built by Barney and Smith), circa 1900 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
    - 3/4 view of buffet/baggage car 2259 with decorative railings and miller coupler, photo taken from buffet end, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2345 with miller coupler and sheet metal under clerestory end, photo taken from baggage end (built in 1850), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2347 with miller coupler and sheet metal under clerestory end, photo taken from baggage end (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1875), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2357 with miller coupler and sheet metal under clerestory end, photo taken from smoking end, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2358 with miller coupler and decorative railing, photo taken from smoking end (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1888), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2383 with miller coupler and round roof (built in 1888), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2407 with miller coupler and round roof, photo taken from baggage end (built in 1850), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - Interior view of combination baggage and smoking 2407 with gas ceiling lamps, photo taken from smoking end, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 2408 with miller coupler, sheet metal under clerestory end and decorative railings (built by Laconia Car Co. in 1880), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - Interior view of combination baggage and smoking 2408 with longitudinal seating, subway type ceiling straps, and slatted wood covered windows (built by Laconia Car Company in 1880), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
    - Interior view of combination car 2714 with gas ceiling lamps, photo taken from passenger end, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
    - 3/4 view of wooden mail/baggage/smoking 2777, photo taken from smoking end, circa 1903 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
    - Vertical interior view of mail/baggage/smoking 2777 shows radiators, photo taken from mail end, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage/newspaper car 2827 with flat roof and knuckle couplers, circa 1903 (Box 2:, Folder 55)
    - Interior view of baggage/newspaper car 2827 with oil lamps and flat roof, circa 1903 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
    - Interior view of baggage/newspaper car 2928 with gas ceiling lamps and clerestory roof, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 57)
    - End view of horse and baggage 2969 showing lowered ramp to load horses, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 58)
    - Interior view of mail/baggage 3152, shows mail racks and pigeon holes, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
    - 3/4 view of wooden mail and baggage 3161 with miller coupler, open vestibule and ornamental end gates, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 60)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage and smoking car 3171 (built by Naugatuck Railroad in 1882), circa 1903 (Box 2:, Folder 61)
    - 3/4 view of wooden mailcar 3263 with closed vestibule and miller coupler (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1896), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 62)
    - 3/4 view of wooden mail 3266 (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1900, appears new), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 63)
    - Interior view of mail car 3266 shows racks for mail sacks, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 64)
    - 3/4 view of Direct Current Electric Trailer 3525, trolley size, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 65)
    - 3/4 view of wooden combination baggage and smoking 3704 with miller coupler and sheet metal under clerestory roof, modified for electric service-equipped with control cab (whistle, gong, and pilot), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 66)
    - Vertical interior view of Express/Mail/Baggage 3902 (trolley car size) shows partition, pigeon holes and swivel chairs, with gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 67)
    - Interior view of Express/Mail/Baggage 3902 (trolley car size) shows cage portion, pigeon holes, swivel chairs, and gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 68)
    - 3/4 view of Electric Mail and Express 4000 with monitor roof, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 69)
    - Interior view of Electric Mail and Express 4000 shows wire partition and pigeon holes, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 70)
  - Baggage cars
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2846, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 71)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2882 (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1886), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 72)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2885 "Builder" (built in 1891), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 73)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2885, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 74)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2928 not opaqued, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 75)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2935, (built by Old Colony Railroad in 1874), circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 76)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2958 with monitor roof, circa 1900 (Box 2:, Folder 77)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 2965 with full clerestory roof (built by Bradley in 1872, rebuilt in 1925), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 78)
    - 3/4 view of wooden baggage car 3140 suburban service, built for elevated railway clearances (built by Wason in 1892), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 79)
    - 3/4 view of steel baggage car 5405 American Railway Express, rebuilt from postal car 3279, circa 1920 (Box 3:, Folder 80)
  - Parlor cars
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor 2112 with miller coupler and large windows, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 81)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2112 with individual stuffed chairs, ornamental woodwork, and gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 82)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2112 with individual stuffed chairs, ornamental woodwork, and gas ceiling lamps (opposite end of the car), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 83)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2124 with ornamental woodwork, gas ceiling lamps and individual stuffed chairs, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 84)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2127 with miller coupler, narrow vestibule and ornamental windowtops. (built by Pullman Co. in 1885), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 85)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2127 with stuffed individual fringed chairs, plus end sofa, gas ceiling lamp and ornamental clerestory, woodwork, and baggage rack, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 86)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2129, miller coupler, narrow vestibule and ornamental windowtops (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1887), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 87)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2129 with very ornamental woodwork, baggage rack and clerestory glass, gas ceiling lamps, stuffed individual fringed chairs, and end sofa (built by New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad in 1887), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 88)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2129 with very ornamental woodwork, baggage rack, and clerestory glass, gas ceiling lamp, stuffed individual fringed chairs and end sofa, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 89)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2153 with ornamental baggage rack, and clerestory glass, gas ceiling lamps, individual stuffed tassle chairs, and wicker end chairs, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 90)
    - Side view of wooden parlor car 2156 with miller coupler and narrow vestibule (built by Barney and Smith in 1893), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 91)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2163 with miller coupler, narrow vestibule and decorative windowtops, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 92)
    - Side view of wooden parlor car 2169 with miller coupler, narrow vestibule, and decorative windowtops, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 93)
    - Side view of wooden parlor car 2169 with miller coupler, narrow vestibule and decorative windowtops, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Vertical interior view of parlor car 2169 with individual stuffed tassle chairs, wicker end chairs with ornamental baggage rack and clerestory glass and gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 95)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2171 with closed vestibule and miller coupler (built by Barney and Smith in 1893), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 96)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2174 with arched decorative windowtops, not opaqued (built by Pullman Co. in 1900), circa 1903 (Box 3:, Folder 97)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2174 with individual stuffed tassle chairs and cut glass gas ceileing lamps (built by Pullman Co. in 1900), circa 1903 (Box 3:, Folder 98)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2174 with arched decorative windowtops (built by Pullman Co. in 1900), circa 1903 (Box 3:, Folder 99)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2174 with individual stuffed tassle chairs and cut glass gas ceiling lamps (opposite end from image above), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 100)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor car 2178 with closed vestibule, decorative arched windows, circa 1903 (Box 3:, Folder 101)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2178 with individual stuffed tassle chairs, and cut glass gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 102)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2178 with non-tassled individual chairs (built by Pullman Company), circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 103)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2178 includes writing desk, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 104)
    - Interior view of parlor car 2178 with individual stuffed tassle chairs and cut glass gas ceiling lamps, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 105)
    - 3/4 view of wooden parlor/observation car 2181 with row of knuckle couplers in foreground, photo taken from observation end, circa 1903 (Box 3:, Folder 106)
    - Interior view of parlor/observation car 2181 with plain chairs, has writing desks and cut glass gas ceiling lamp, photo taken from observation end, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 107)
    - Interior view of observation/parlor car 2181 with stuffed tassle chairs, photo taken from parlor section, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 108)
    - Interior view of passenger car - carpeted but no seats, possibly a parlor car, circa 1900 (Box 3:, Folder 109)
  - Sleeping/State Room cars